Welcome back. In this lesson, we are locking two powerful tools and TypeScript, Union types,
and intersection types. So these let us combine types to create flexible, expressive, and
safe data structures. So whether you're modeling user inputs, perhaps API responses, or even
component props, these tools are essential for you. So first of all, let's have a look at Union
types. So Union type, let's have value B or one of several types. And that sounds a bit strange,
but think of it as saying, this type can be either A or it could be B. That's kind of weird, right?
To be this kind of one or the other. So let me show you what I mean. So let me do let ID,
colon, and it could be a string, or that's with a pipe symbol, it could be a number,
like I have a string or a number, because one of those two things. So you could do, for example,
ID, and it could be maybe like one. That's fine, because there's a string, or we could do ID equals one,
and it's a number, or we could do ID equals APC, 123, and it could be ID equals 42 as a number.
If we do ID equals a boolean, like this, we get an issue. In fact, the ID is not allowed,
because there's not a signable to either a string or a number. And of course, we could fix this
by saying it could be a boolean as well, but coming up to here, and then the error goes away.
So this is a perfect for cases where a valley might come from multiple formats, perhaps an ID
from a database, or perhaps someone types it on an input box, for example, and then it's a string.
So let's have a look at a few things. So let's have a look at another example. So this
perhaps we could have a union type with the literal values. So like we did from the last lesson,
we could have a type of alignment, and the alignment could be a left. It would be center,
or it could be right. And then we can have a variable. So you text a line of type,
alignment, and we can assign it to center. That's fine. But if we try and assign it to something
like justify, then it's going to complain, because it's not one of those three options.
We could also say, for example, that we have alignment, and it could also be a number.
Not sure why, but you might want to do like that. And you could do, for example, test, text a line,
equals, it could be left, and no errors there. We could also assign it to a number, perhaps, 23.
And that also works because we've got alignment and number, of course, so spell alignment wrong.
So it just could be fixed. There we go, alignment or number.
Now let's move on and have a look at intersection types. So an intersection type combines
multiple types into one. So think of it as saying, this must be a and b. So where we has the
previous one, which is union types, which was a or b, an intersection type is a and b.
So let's have to make examples, of course. So let's have a type of person. And the name,
let's set this string.
And we're going to have another type of employee.
And the employee ID is a number.
And now let's do something like staff, remember a staff, that this a staff is a person,
but usually they are, unless the AI nowadays, and we also have an employee.
So both of these types need to be true through a staff type.
So now we can actually define, say, for example, Bob, Bob is a teacher, and he is a member of staff.
And his name is Bob, which is a string, and he is employee ID number 101.
Now what happens if we take away one of these properties, let's take away the employee ID.
And then we usually get an error that it's not a signable because we are missing
or one of the properties. Now you can start to see how type scripts really
start and become quite powerful because it's enforcing us to have to have one of these
particular properties. So now as soon as we put our employee ID back, then it's happy.
Of course, if we try to assign it to a string, say 101, it's not going to be happy about that,
only if it's a string and a number. So let's take a look at another example of this intersection
type in action. So we're going to define a type. Once I can spell it, there it is of, say,
contact info. And the contact info, we're going to have a string for now, for an email,
and we're also going to have a login info. And this has two properties, a username,
of type string, the password, of type string. And now we want to use a account,
the user account is going to be made up of contact information. And maybe we can put
bounds in here, log in info. So both of those to be user accounts. And now we can define a user,
the user is of type user account. And we need to find these. So we need the first one,
the email, what satisfies email. So let's just put us at example.com.
And also need the username. So Alice. And also need the password, super strong password,
or password. And now it satisfies that and a red line goes away. So we're managing to
define two properties this time on this login information, we're both the type in contact info
and the login info. Let's have a look at some comparisons when to use union versus when to use
intersection. So you should use union when you want to allow multiple possibilities when
something is something when something is something when something is either A or B. But you use
intersection when you want to combine multiple requirements together. And the back on union,
you want to use union when we're modeling input formats, perhaps all status varies values,
whereas intersection could be used or merging interfaces or perhaps composing data models.
And you can also use union when you want to handle optional or variants properties,
whereas intersection is more useful for building reusable or layered types. So both union and
intersection types gives us control on how types interacts union say basically either slash or
whereas intersection say both slash and.